我像块石头
I am a stone.
纹丝不动
I do not move.
我慢慢地把雪放进嘴里
Very slowly, I put snow in my mouth,
这样 狼就看不见我的呼气
then he won't see my breath.
我耐心等待 等它再靠近些
I take my time. I let him come closer.
我只有一发子弹
I have only one bullet.
我瞄准狼的眼睛
I aim at his eye.
手指放在扳掣上
Very gently,my finger presses on the trigger.
我不发抖
I do not tremble.
也不害怕
I have no fear.
我已经是个大孩子了
I'm a big boy now.
准备 瓦希里！
Ready,Vassili?
瓦希里 开枪！
Now,Vassili. Fire!
开枪 瓦希里！
Fire,Vassili! Fire!
兵临城下
快 快 抓紧时间
Come on,pick your feet up.
起来 起来 准备上车
Get on your feet. Prepare to board the train.
现在跟我来 这边 伙计
You there,come along with me now. This way,pal.
大家起来
All civilians,get out!
起来 准备上火车 快走
Make way,let the civilians off.
这是部队专车
This is a military convoy.
除了英勇的军人 所有人都下车
No one stays on board but our valiant soldiers.
这是护送红军
This is a convoy
前往斯大林格勒的专车
to Stalingrad...
本列车只接载我们的英勇军人
only for the soldiers of the Red Army.
这是护送红军
This is a military convoy.
前往斯大林格勒的专车
to Stalingrad...
到齐
All aboard!
1942年秋季
Autumn,1942.
纳粹党的军队横行欧洲
Europe lies crushed beneath the Nazi jackboot.
德意志第三帝国势头正盛
The German Third Reich I sat the height of its power.
正攻入苏联心脏
Hitler's armies are charging through the heart of the Soviet Union...
向中东的油田进发
towards the oilfields of Asia.
他们只剩下一道防线
One last obstacle remains.
全球命运全系于… 伏尔加河畔一个城市
A city on the Volga... where the fate of the world is being decided.
斯大林格勒
Stalingrad.
所有军队和市民
The Red Army and all citizens of the Soviet Union
势必捍卫苏维埃的每一寸领土 决战到底
must defend every inch of Soviet soil.Must fight to the last.
1942年9月20日
斯大林同志有令：绝不后退
Glorious comrade Stalin... has ordered not another step backwards.
苏联人民要争取自由
The people of the Soviet Union shall be free.
决不沦为奴隶
Never gonna be a slaves！
同志们 前进！
Go forward,comrades.
一步也不能后退
Not a step backwards!
这些信是苏联母亲写给
Listen to these letters sent by Russian mothers...
在前线的儿子 听听吧
to their sons on the front.
瓦洛亚 我儿…
"Volodya,my child,
我知道这是为了祖国
I know that it's for our motherland一
我知道你是为国捐躯
"I know that it's for our motherland that you are giving your life.
大家都知道你绝不退缩
"Everyone here knows that you will not fall back.
大家都以你为荣
"Everyone here is proud of you.
你父亲死了 兄弟死了
"Your father is dead. Your brothers are dead.
你要向法西斯党讨回这份血债
Avenge us on the hordes of fascists. "
趴下！…
Everybody drops here!
找掩护！
Find coverd！
一 不准动 一 留在船上
Nobody move! Stay on the boat!
回来 否则开枪！
Get back or I'll shoot!
回来 否则我们就开枪！ 枪毙叛徒！
Back from the rails,or we shoot. Shoot the traitors!
斯大林格勒码头
准备上岸！
Ready ashore!
快 快 走
Come on,come on! Move!
快点 同志们
Come on,comrades,
Come on,comrades, come on!
快走 否则会被击中!
Move,or you'll be shot!
这边！分开
Over here,stretcher!
有枪的人就开枪
The one with the rifle shoots!
每两个人一支枪
One out of two gets a rifle.
有枪的人走前 没枪的人随后
The one without follows him!
有枪的人倒下了…
When the one with the rifle gets killed,
尾随的人 就检起枪 继续射击
the one who is following picks up the rifle and shoots!
有枪的人就开枪
The one with the rifle shoots!
没枪的人随后
The one without follows him!
有枪的人倒下了…
When the one with the rifle gets killed,
尾随的人就检起枪 继续射击
the one who is following... picks up the rifle and shoots!
有枪的人就开枪 走这边 没枪的人随后
The one with the rifle shoots! This way,now.The one without follows him!
伟大的红军士兵
Soldiers of the glorious Red Army,
现在起 我们不成功便成仁
from now on...it is either victory or death!
违抗命令者 按军法处置 我需要枪
一 Those who retreat will be shot. 一 I need a rifle.
懦夫和叛徒 坚决就地正法
There will be no mercy For cowards and traitors! Achtung!
Aah!
无望的了 同志们！撤退！
It's hopeless,comrades. Get back!
撤退！…
Pullback!
Pullback! Get back! Get back!
奉苏联之名…
In the name of the Soviet Union,
你们不准后退 否则被杀！
not a step backwards, or we shoot.
不准后退半步！
No retreat! Not a step back!
绝不宽待 逃兵将被击毙!懦夫将被抢毙!
一 No mercy! 一 Deserters will be shot. Cowards will be shot!
开枪！
一 Fire! 一 Shoot the traitors!
枪毙叛徒！
Cowards will be shot!
绝不宽待懦夫！
No mercy for cowards!
俄罗斯人 投降吧！
Russians,surrender.
投降就可以重返家园
You will see your home again.
这场仗不关你们事
This is not your war.
加入德军 他们体恤你们的苦况
Join your German comrades, They understand your suffering...
比你们的军官更关心你们
and will care more for you than your own officers,
你们的军官只派你们去送死
who are only sending you to your death.
第三帝国不是你们的敌人
The Third Reich Is not your enemy.
你们的敌人是嗜血的斯大林
The enemy is blood thirsty Stalin And his Bolshevik camp,
与他的党徒 他们抢走你们的土地 驱逐你们的父亲
who have stolen your land,who have deported your father一
开火！
Fire!
不容许敌人踏足斯大林格勒
政委同志 这样我们会被发现的
You'll get us caught, comrade Commissar.
政委同志 请让我来
With your permission, comrade Commissar.
应该先杀哪一个?
Which one should I aim at first?
应该先等爆炸才开枪
You should wait...till there's an explosion.
你懂开枪吗?
Do you know how to shoot?
一点点
A little.
该死!
Damn!Damn!
别开枪 他发现我们了
Don't shoot. Don't shoot. He's looking at us.
谢谢你 政委同志
Thank you, comrade Commissar.
丹尼洛夫 第21步兵团
Danilov,political officer, second class.
第二政治委员
Twenty一 first infantry.
瓦希里柴瑟夫
"Vassili Zaitsev."
1942年9月20日…
"On this day, September the 20th,1942,
一名来自乌拉尔的年轻牧羊人
"a shepherd boy from the Urals...
抵达伏尔加河畔的斯大林格勒
"arrived in the city of Stalingrad, on the banks of the Volga.
他名叫瓦希里柴瑟夫
"His name is Vassili Zaitsev.
他是响应斯大林同志的号召而来
"Like thousands before him,he came to answer comrade Stalin's call.
只拿着一支枪…
"Armed with a rifle,
就很快令纳粹侵略者意识到…
he quickly made the fascist invader realize that...
他们不及早回头
"from now on he would be punished for every step he took in the motherland;
只有死路一条
that from here on, the only way was back."
觉得怎样?
What do you think?
我认为政委同志太过奖了
I think comrade Commissar's been overgenerous.
1942年9月22日
放我过去！ 放我过去！
Let me go! Let me go!
不准越线！
Don't cross the line!
斯大林同志有令：民众不得离城
By order of comrade Stalin, no civilian can leave the city.
回去！
Get back!
放我过去！
Let me go!
走开 否则我们开枪！
Stand away, or we will open fire.
走开!
Stand away!
走开！
Get back!
回去 否则我们开枪！
Get back or we shoot!
走开…
Back! Keep back!
给斯大林同志的特使让路
Make way for comrade Stalin 's envoy!
我有执行命令
I carried out my orders.
派遣了所有士兵
I sent in all of my boys.
不过 敌我军力悬殊
But the Germans engulfed us.
他们有大炮、飞机、坦克…
They have artillery, aircraft,tanks.
我们呢?有什么?
And me,what did I have?
死守的神圣任务
The sacred duty to resist!
我必须报告最高领袖
I have to report to the boss.
你最好自我了断
Perhaps you'd prefer to avoid the red tape.
我叫…
My name is...
尼吉达.卓基域治.赫鲁晓夫
Nikita Sergeyevich Kruschev.
我来接管这里
I've come to take things in hand here.
这里不是库斯克
This city is not Kursk...
不是基辅 也不是明斯克
nor is it Kiev,nor Minsk.
而是斯大林格勒
This city is Stalingrad.
斯大林…格勒
Stalingrad!
本市背负着领袖的名字
This city bears the name of the boss.
不仅是个城市 更是个标志
It's more than a city, it's a symbol.
假如德军占领了这里
If the Germans capture this city,
全国就会瓦解
the entire country will collapse.
现在我希望士兵们昂起头来！
Now,I want our boys... to raise their heads.
我要他们拿出勇气来！
I want them to act like they have balls!
不准他们再怕得屎滚尿流！
I want them to stop shitting their pants!
你们是政委
That's your job.
激励士气是你们的职责
As political officers, I'm counting on you.
你 你有什么建议?
You, what's your suggestion?
把退缩的将军、参谋长统统枪毙
Shoot all the other generals who have retreated... and their chiefs of staff too.
立下范例
M-Make some examples.
放逐逃兵的家属 做过了
一 D - D - Deport families of the deserters.一 Yeah,that's all been done.
给士兵希望
Give them hope!
他们现在不是死于敌军就是我军
Here,the men's only choice is between German bullets and ours.
不过 还有另一条路
But there's another way.
就是勇气之路、爱国之路
The way of courage.The way of love of the motherland.
我们必须再次印发军报
We must publish the army newspaper again.
报导英勇事迹 歌颂报国精神
We must tell magnificent stories. Stories that extol... sacrifice,bravery.
确立必胜信念
We must make them believe in the victory.
燃点群众的希望 激发斗志
We must give them hope, pride,a desire to fight.
是的 我们要立下范例
Yes,we need to make examples.
但那是供人学习的范例
But examples to follow.
我们需要…
What we need...
英雄
are heroes.
这里有英雄?
Do you know any heroes around here?
有 同志 我认识一个
Yes,comrade, I know one.
那是我！
That's me!
瓦希里！那是我！
"Vassili Zaitsev." That's me!
你没做梦
No,you're not dreaming.
的确是你的名字！
It's your name.
我们的文章上了头版！
We made the front page.
他们一字不改！
They haven't changed a word.
你知道这意味着什么吗
Do you have any idea what this means?
不是尾页 也不是第二页
It's not the back page, it's not the second page,
是头版！
It's the front page.
头版！
The front page!
全国各地都会转载我们的文章
They're going to reprint our article everywhere.
高加索、克里米亚
In the Caucasus,in the Crimea,
甚至乌拉尔
even in the Urals.
明早斯大林会边吃早餐
Tomorrow morning,Stalin himself will be sitting over breakfast,
读着我的文章 记得你的名字
reading my words, memorizing your name.
我们一举成名了 瓦希里
We're famous,Vassili.
赫鲁晓夫喜欢这篇文章
Kruschev loved the article.
他把我升为参谋
He's promoted me to the general staff.
而你呢
And you
就调去狙击队
to sniper division.
好极！  十分好！
一 Well,that's good. 一 It's very good.
好得很！  好极了
一 It's very good. It's great. 一 It's very great!一 It's great!
你我合作的成果 因为共同努力
一 For us because we did it together. 一 Together!
我比较辛苦 是吗
一 Although I did all the hard work. 一 Oh,yeah?
你走运 我不能还手  为什么
一 You're very lucky I can't fight back. 一 Why's that?
赫鲁晓夫要我保障你安全
Because Kruschev told me to make sure nothing happens to you.
你现在很重要 我很有价值
一 You're too important. 一 I'm too valuable.
小心我的眼镜 对不起
Yes,careful of my一  careful of my glasses,please. They're new. Sorry,sir.
我成名了！我们成名了！
一 I'm famous! We're famous! 一 I'm famous! I'm famous!
来自乌拉尔的瓦希里
Vassili, the young shepherd from the Urals,
今天杀了第12名德军！
killed his 12th German officer today.
他从前杀狼 现在杀敌
He used to hunt wolves, Now he shoots fascists.
瓦希里今天杀了第23名德军！
Today,Vassili Zaitsev shot his 23rd German officer.
又有一名上校毙命  瓦希里是我们的榜样
One more colonel shot by... He is an example to us all.
瓦希里今天杀了第32名德军！
Today Vassili shot his 32nd German officer.
他有猎人的毅力
He has patience of a hunter.
有俄罗斯人的毅力
He has patience of Russia people.
今天杀了第46名德军！
你们消灭了多少德国兵
Count only the Germans you have killed.
瓦希里今天杀了第35名德军！
一 Today,Vassili Zaitsev一  一 Here is the evidence一
瓦希里三日内取得十一个军牌
11 dog tags retrieved by sniper Vassili Zaitsev.
瓦希里大名 令我军肃然起敬
令敌军闻风丧胆
我们的战士…
More and more men and women,
不分男女 越来越多…
fighters from all branches of our armed forces,
志愿加入狙击队…
join the sniper division
向瓦希里学习
and learn the skills of Vassili Zaitsev.
我像块石头
I am a stone.
我纹丝不动
我放轻呼吸
I breathe slowly.
我瞄准目标
I aim at the eye.
你就是…
So it is you,
大名鼎鼎的瓦希里！
the great Vassili Zaitsev.
我妈妈烧得一手顶级烟肉薯仔
My mother makes potatoes with bacon.
听来不错
Sounds good.
她要是见到你 准会乐坏
When she sees you, she won't believe her eyes.
今天杀了几个?
How many today?
只有两个
Only two.
最后那个为何不杀?
And the last one, why didn't you shoot him?
他只是个步兵
He was only a foot soldier.
不值得为了他而暴露我的行踪
Wasn't worth giving away my position.
愿上帝保佑你
一 Bless you.
我们欠你很多
We know how much we owe you.
我们每天都为你祈祷
We pray for you every day.
我们每晚都听电台对你的报导
Every evening,we listen to them talk about you on Radio Moscow.
谢谢
Thanks.
你们这地下室相当不错
You've certainly managed well down here.
战前我父母在这里堆放家具
My parents used to store furniture down here before the war.
沙夏！把枪放下！
Sacha,drop that right now.
里面有子弹的
It's loaded.
政委同志 这里请
This way,comrade Commissar.
谢谢你 同志
Thank you,comrade.
各位好
Good evening.
瓦希里同志
Comrade Zaitsev?
好多信 从哪里寄来的?
My God,where does all this mail come from?
全国各地都有
From all over the country, Mrs.Filipov,from all over.
库兹巴斯的矿工来信说…
This one's from the workers of the Kouzbass.
打算把矿场命名为瓦希里矿场
They want to name their mine after Vassili.
先答矿工的信吧
Right,let's start with the miners.
开始吧
Come on, let's get to work.
库兹巴斯的同志 你们好
Dear comrades from the Kouzbass,
多谢你们的赞扬
一 Kouzbass. 一 I thank you for your letter of praise.
“称赞”怎样串?  PRAISE
一 Praise?  - R - A - I - S - E.
还有 希望我能不负所望
And... I hope that I can live up...
不负所望…
to your expectations. - A - T - I - O - N - S. Expectations.
费太太 你对德国文学有兴趣?
You're interested in German literature,Mrs.Filipov?
不要紧 她是邻居
It's all right, it's our neighbor.
写到哪里?  不负所望
一 Right,where were we?
丹尼娅 我们有客人
一 Tania,we have guests.
你提议命名…
Your offer to name-
我
I-
我…我认得你…
I - I recognize you.
他是瓦希里！
He's Vassili Zaitsev.
我在报纸上看过你的照片
I saw your picture in the paper.
感谢你所做的一切
Thank you For everything you're doing.
这位是他朋友 政委…
And this is his friend,Commissar.....
丹尼洛夫
Danilo
Danilov.
我把丹尼娅当作亲生女
Tania is like a daughter to me.
我在工厂干活时 沙夏由她照顾
She used to take care of Sacha when I worked at the factory.
她甚至教沙夏德语
She even taught him German.
这些书都是她的 是你的?
一 All these books are hers. 一 Oh,they're yours?
她在大学读德文
She studied German at the university.
哪间大学?  莫斯科大学
一 Which university? 一 Moscow.
莫斯科
Moscow. Moscow.
要不要…
Shouldn't we,uh-
好 继续覆信
Yes,let's continue.
你们提议把矿场要以我命名
Your offer to name Your mine after me...
我深感荣幸
is... a great honor.
HON… 我懂得串“荣幸”
H - O - N. Yes,I know. Honor.
很好
Very good.
应不应该…
Shouldn't we
强调不只我孤军作战?
Shouldn't we try make the point that I'm not the only one fighting?
你说得有道理 瓦西里 好主意
That - That's excellent - excellent idea,Vassili.
可以在下面阐明 嗯
一 We can take it even further though. 一 Oh.
对 下面阐明
We can take it further.
你们为挖煤而奋斗…
Your battle for The production of coal...
所作出的贡献一样重要
is as worthy as mine.
“煤”没有K字
There's no "K" in coal.
只有一个L字 对了
Just - just one "L."
我是不是说得太快?
Oh,tell me if I'm going too fast.
你说得不太快 真的吗?
一 No,you're not going too fast. 一 You sure?
我希望自己有进步
I just thought is there Any other improvements?
你们休息一会吧
Why don't you get some rest?
信可以明天再写
These letters can wait until tomorrow.
我们要继续写
We should carry on.
我们不累 谢谢关心 费太太
We're not tired.Thank you,Mrs.Filipov.
这些人水深火热中一番热诚写信来
These people... took the trouble to write to us.
我们明天未必有机会回覆
Tomorrow,we may not be around to write back.
1942年10月21日德军总部
将军 康尼少校到
Major Konig, Herr General.
我早知道柏林会派人来
I was expecting someone... else.
但没想到是鼎鼎大名的你
Certainly not someone so prestigious.
你肯插手这棘手的事 必有原因
I imagine you have your reasons... for getting yourself involved in this hellish situation.
我军不习惯这种作战方式
My army is not designed For this kind of fighting.
昨天我要提升25个沙展
Yesterday,yet again, I had to promote...25 sergeants
代替那些死于狙击手枪下的军官
to replace the officers shot down by their sharpshooters.
那些狙击手使我军士气大挫
Those snipers are demoralizing my people.
这个城市如同一堆残垣断瓦
This city is no more than... a heap of ruins.
不过 元首还要穷追猛打
But the fuehrer's persisting.
藉此解决他和斯大林的私人恩怨
He has made it a personal matter between Stalin and himself.
我们应该信赖元首的直觉
We should trust the fuehrer's instinct.
他一向带领我们取得胜利
He always managed to lead us to victory.
我们可以回家度圣诞
We shall be back home For Christmas.
你打算怎样找这年轻的俄人?
How are you going to go about finding this young Russian?
我会安排好 让他来找我
I'll fix it so that he's the one who finds me.
瓦希里
Vassili. Vassili.
是时候起床 什么事?
一 Come on,time to get up. 一 What?
百货公司那里有麻烦 需要帮忙
They have a problem in the department store sector. They need us. Come on.
那狙击手躲在百货公司里面
Look,Vassili,he's hiding in the department store. Over there.
今早到现在
So far this morning,
他已经干掉了五个军官和两个机关枪手
he's knocked off five officers, plus two machine gunners.
看！三楼
Look,third floor,
左边第四扇窗
fourth window from the left.
Fourth window from the left.
看到他吗?
See him?
看到
Yeah,I see him.
射中了！
There,you got him!
好枪法！
Great shot.
去拿他的军牌吧
Let's go get his dog tag.
再见 政委同志
Good bye,comrade Commissar.
感谢你的款待 费太太
Thank you for your hospitality,Mrs.Filipov.
随便借阅好了
You can borrow whatever you like.
捧着一堆哥德、雪莱作品回去…
I'm not sure what they would say to me at headquarters...
总部的人会说闲话的
if I came back with an armful of Goethe and Schiller.
我也有马克思的作品
There's some Marx too.
你被调去第12区做民兵
You were assigned to civil defense at the 12th district?
不 我是自愿的
No,I volunteered.
能遇见你 真巧 赫鲁晓夫同志…
It's such a coincidence meeting you like this.
昨天才对我说…
Comrade Kruschev was telling me just yesterday...
我们极需要会德语的通讯员
how desperately we're in need of operators who speak German.
不可以
I can't.
我们的部队负责本区的安全
Our militia's responsible for all the people in this neighbourhood.
人手已经很短缺  那好办
We're already desperately short of men.
我们愿意用十二个士兵交换你
We'll give you a dozen soldiers for every one that speaks German.
我宁愿留下来作战
I'd rather stay and fight.
服务总部也是作战 你会更有用
Serving at headquarters is fighting. You'd be far more useful there.
你留下来 掩护我们
You stay here. You cover us.
好
All right.
我们去了
We go.
保重
Take care.
露米娜 来
Ludmilla,come on.
查看楼梯！
Check the stairway.
这是个圈套 我知道
It's a trap. I know.
撤退
Move back.
他还在这里
He's still here.
他们正轰炸过来！
They're coming straight for us!
露米娜 留在原地 他就在我们附近
Ludmilla,stay where you are, he's over there somewhere.
我们得离开这里！
We have to get out of here!
不走不行！
不要动！
Just stay where you are!
怎办?  留在原地别动！
What are we gonna do? Ludmilla,stay where you are!
我不管！我要走了
Fuck this,I'm going.
露米娜 不要走！
Ludmilla,no!
上面写的是什么?
What does this mean?
瓦希里获发新的狙击枪
"The little shepherd from the Urals receives a new sniper's rifle,
莫纳7.62型 配备3.5倍望远镜
"a Mosin - Nagant 7.62, with its 3.5 - power P.U. telescope.
苏联最得意的精良武器
Pride of precision Of Soviet production."
我看过那支枪 是吗?
一 I've seen that rifle close up. 一 Have you?
甚至摸过
I've even touched it.
我跟瓦希里很熟的…
I know him well,Vassili Zaitsev.
苏联总部的码头
露米娜和安东今天死了
Ludmilla and Anton were killed today,
都是我的错
and it was my fault.
我肯定这不是事实
No,I'm sure that's not true.
冒出个德军狙击手
There was a German sniper.
我带他们中了他的圈套
I walked them right into his trap.
你还知道什么?
What else can you tell me?
他没有转移阵地
He didn't relocate.
狙击手不转移阵地…
A sniper who doesn't relocate
是不合常规的
isn't normal.
他很厉害
He was very good.
不仅枪法好 而且有很准的直觉
It wasn't just his shooting,it was his instinct.
他的行动往往比我早一步
He was a step ahead of me all the time.
那是因为他对你了如指掌
That's because he knows everything about you.
他叫康尼 康尼少校
His name is Konig, Major Konig.
德军派他来
They've sent him here
是为了杀…找你
to ki...to find you.
我们起初不知道线报是否可靠
At first we weren't sure if the information was reliable.
他似乎专程从柏林来杀你
It seems he's come all the way from Berlin to stop you.
你令他们寝食难安 他们派高手来置你于死地
You've caused them so many sleepless nights,they sent their top marksman.
他是什么来头?
What do we know about him?
他是德军的少校
He's a major in the Wehrmacht.
在佐森担任狙击训练所所长
He's director of their sniper school in Zossen.
战前 科里哥夫跟过他学习
Koulikov studied under him at Zossen before the war.
很清楚他的伎俩
He knows all his tricks.
由现在起 你去哪里 他去哪里
From now on, he'll go with you everywhere.
来自巴伐利亚的猎鹿贵族
A nobleman from Bavaria who hunts deer...
跟来自乌拉尔的杀狼小子对决
against a shepherd boy from the Urals who poaches wolves.
这不仅是两国之战
It's more than a confrontation between two nations.
也标志着阶级斗争的精髓
It's the essence Of class struggle.
很高兴你这样兴奋
I'm glad you're so happy.
他占尽上风
He had all the advantages.
下次你会打平
Next time you'll be even.
你的枪法所向无敌
No one shoots like you,Vassili.
她被调职了
She's been transferred.
我去看看隔壁准备好了没有
I'll see if they're ready for you next door.
你好
Hello.
你穿上新制服好英俊
You look smart in your new uniform.
结束后别交还
Make sure they don't take it back once you've finished.
可能要交还
Yeah,they probably will.
我听过那德国人的事
I've heard the rumor about the German,
祝你好运
and I wanted to wish you luck.
谢谢 我现在很需要运气
Thank you. I'll need it.
丹尼洛夫同志说…
From what comrade Danilov tells me,
你稳操胜券
you're going to win.
Hmm.
是时候了
It's time.
瓦希里…这边！来拥抱一下
一  Vassili! Vassili! 一 Come to my arms.
望过来 瓦希里
Look in my direction.
戴着帽吧 这样更似英雄
Put your cap back on, you look more heroic.
这边 瓦希里同志
This way,comrade Zaitsev.
这小伙子甚得我心！
I love this little fellow.
瓦希里 你真的自愿上前线?
Vassili,is it true that you volunteered for the front?
你几岁?
How old are you,Vassili?
你知道这对国家有多大意义吗?
Do you know what this duel means for our country?
你是不是五岁就杀狼?
Is it true you killed your first wolf when you were five?
你今天杀了多少德军?
Vassili,tell me how many officers had been kill today?
德国派神枪手对付你 你自豪吗
Are you proud to be challenged By the best sharpshooter in Germany?
这表示德国鬼开始怕我们了
The Germans are starting to shit their pants.
对他们讲你怎样对付他吧
Go on,my boy,tell us how you're going to deal with him.
还是别对他们讲 问多一个问题
一 Or rather,no.一 One more question,please.
对领袖讲吧！
Tell it to the boss.
他喜欢听追猎的故事
He likes good hunting stories.
挺起胸膛看着他
Look at him with pride,
因为他正看着你
because he's looking at you.
全国正看着你
The whole country is looking at you.
原谅我吧 爷爷
Forgive me,forgive me, Grandfather.
1942年10月23日
狩猎场不是由狼决定
So,it's not the wolf that chooses the hunting ground...
是由猎人决定的
but the hunter.
你爷爷必定教过你
But I'm sure your grandfather taught you that.
不过 今次我是猎物
Except in this case, I'm the game.
不管怎样 今天我们要引狼出窦
However, today what we're going to do... is lure the wolf out of his lair...
把狼引到我们要狼到的地方
to where we want him to be.
你的命值钱 你先跳
You're the one whose life is valuable. You go first.
不 我们轮流先跳
No,no. We take it in turns.
下次 轮到你先跳
Next time is your turn to go first,
然后轮到你 伏洛迪亚
and then it's you,Volodya.
混蛋
Son of a bitch!
滚开！
Get off!
这裤子是新的
These are new pants.
我昨天才从一名队长身上脱下来
I just took them Off a captain from the 25 1st yesterday.
我在德国的佐森…
Sixteen months I spent in Germany
待了16个月
at the school in Zossen.
当然那时我们还没跟德国佬交恶
Of course,those were the days when we were friends with the Krauts,:
我们的斯大林跟他们的希特勒
when our Joseph and their Adolph...
当时还在称兄道弟
were walking hand in hand.
这里离电线有160米吧?
From here to the wire, 160meters,right?
155… One hundred and fifty-five.
无所谓
Whatever.
这一来 他们要派人来修理
That'll make 'em Send out a repair guy.
转移阵地吧
Let's relocate.
Aah!
伏洛迪亚！
Hey,Volodya!
德国侵略我们之后…
After the Germans invaded us,
气氛完全不同了
it wasn't the same atmosphere anymore.
我无辜给人抓去坐牢
Threw my ass in prison.
“你去德国做什么?”
What were you doing in Germany,huh?
我答：抱歉 斯大林同志派我去
Excuse me,says I,but it was comrade Stalin who sent me there.
不要诋毁我们伟大的领袖
Don't bring our glorious leader into your treachery.
认罪吧 奸细
Confess,spy bastard! Confess.
跟着…
And bang! Bang,bang,bang!
他们拿出的不是镰刀 是铁锤
Well,there wasn't a sickle, but there was a hammer.
跟着…
And bang.
把我的牙统统敲掉
Knocked out all my teeth.
对了 小伙子 不要心存幻想
That's right,boy. Have no illusions.
这就是社会主义的天堂
That's the land of socialism and universal bliss for you.
维修的人来了！
Hey! It's your repair guy.
我瞄准了
I got him.
该喝汤了吧?
It's about soup time, isn't it?
我去拿
I'm going.
那还不去?伏洛迪亚
Well,get a move on,Volodya,
不要倒泄 你这马克思混蛋
and try not to spill it all on your way back,you Marxist bastard.
这是过去一天敌军的狙击记录
The enemy sniper activity reported during the past 24 hours,Herr Major.
火车站的两名哨兵被杀害
Two sentries shot in the train station sector.
北区一名大炮观察员遇害
One artillery observer in the Northern sector.
工厂区第24装甲部队一名少尉遇害
One lieutenant from the 24th Panzer division in the factory sector.
工人宿舍三名通讯工兵
Three telephone repairmen in the workers' housing sector.
我们抓到战俘 你或者会感兴趣
They also tell me we have just taken a prisoner who may interest you.
但愿他能开口
I hope he's still able to speak.
什么?少校
Excuse me,sir?
没什么 谢谢
Nothing. Thank you.
伏洛迪亚 他在哪幢楼内?
So,tell us,Volodya, which building is he in?
我不可能知道
There is no way I know that.
他不断走来走去
He moves around all the time.
从一幢楼跳去另一幢
He jumps from one to the next.
在哪一层?
On which floor?
不知道
I don't know.
我们很快会知道
We'll see about that.
把他的衣服脱掉
Undress him.
给他穿上我们的军服
Put him in one of our uniforms.
瞧 还真倔
You see,they are stubborn.
这是德国人的优点
That's the good thing about the Germans.
你得承认 假如他们打定主意…
Man,you got to admit when they get an idea in their heads一
好
Right.
看看顾客来了没有 准备好了吗
Let's see if our customer has arrived. Are you ready?
Uh一huh.
康尼少校眼中的白痴
And now our famous shepherd from the Urals,
我们有名的乌拉尔牧羊人
who Major Konig thinks is an idiot,
站了起来 看看自己是否击中了目标
gets up to make sure he has hit his target.
康尼少校看到他
Major Konig sees him.
瞄准他的头盔…
Aims for his helmet.
开枪
Fires.
他暴露了自己的位置
Reveals his position
反而被射死了
And is shot in turn.
可是…
Except...
康尼少校并没有开枪
Major Konig doesn't fire...
因为康尼少校并不在
because Major Konig isn't there.
科里哥夫
Koulikov!
你不觉得刚才很奇怪吗?
Don't you think that was strange, that last one?
他们明知出来就要被射死
They sent him out to get shot like the others.
这很不寻常
It's not natural.
却依然派人出来 而且不掩护他
Not without artillery, without trying to cover him.
我才是蠢的那个
Oh,no,I'm the one who was stupid.
他们才不在乎通讯兵的死活
They don't give a shit about telephone guys.
就像我们对待乌克兰人一样
I mean,it's like us with the Ukrainians.
死几个乌克兰佬 我们眉也不皱
They'd never bother a major over a few dead grunts.
我们明天杀几个将军吧
Tomorrow,we'll kill us some generals.
轮到谁?
Whose turn is it?
似乎轮到我
Mine,I think.
骗人！
Oh,you're such a cheater!
想骗科里哥夫叔叔?妄想
You can't fool Papa Koulikov.
轮到我先跳
No,no,no,no,no,no,no, it's my turn to go first.
轮到你的裤子被射穿
And it's your turn to get a hole in your britches.
祝我们胜利！
To victory.
狙击决斗的事拖得太久了
This sniper business has been dragging on too long.
你那小子有什么进展?
What's that little fellow of yours up to?
他在试探 赫鲁晓夫同志
He's probing, comrade Kruschev.
试探那德国人的弱点
He's testing the Germans for weaknesses.
他做事一丝不苟
He's meticulous in his preparation.
伏特加这种奢侈品 我们有
Vodka... is a luxury we have.
鱼子酱这种奢侈品 我们有
Caviar is a luxury we have.
时间 我们没有
Time is not.
这点他明白 赫鲁晓夫同志 我俩都明白
He's aware of that comrade Kruschev. We both are.
我保证他会成功 好
I assure you he will succeed. Good.
你俩的命运息息相关
It seems your destinies are entwined.
你相当忙
They're keeping you busy.
我在厨房捡来
I picked this up in the kitchen.
这是前几天的招待会剩下来的
It's from the reception the other day.
我想费太太会喜欢
I thought Mrs.Filipov might like it.
她会很高兴 你真好
Um,she will be thrilled. That's very sweet of you.
你饿的话 还有很多
There's plenty more If you're hungry.
你是犹太教的吧?
You're Jewish, aren't you?
我们的宗教并不禁止吃鲟鱼
There's nothing in our religion that says you can't eat sturgeon.
我爸爸早已预感到这会发生
My father had a premonition all this would happen.
你指预感到战事?
You mean the war?
他知道大家一向都仇恨犹太人
He understood that the hatred of the jews ran deep.
他在储蓄 打算到巴勒斯坦买地
He was saving up to buy some land in Palestine.
还说那儿才是属于我们的地方
He said it was the only land we truly belonged in;
那儿才值得我们保卫
the only land we had a duty to defend.
他一定要我学开枪
He insisted learn to use a rifle.
于是我学会了
I learned to shoot.
我知道打仗时
I know that in times of war,
个人感情要放在一旁
personal feelings should be put aside,but...
但我想请你帮忙
I have a favor to ask you.
没问题 尽管说
Of course. Anything you want.
我想调职
I want to be reassigned.
丹尼娅 怎么了?
What's happened,Tania?
他射死了科里哥夫
He shot him.
第一个跳 也被打死了
He shot him even though he jumped first.
跳过去时中弹
Shot him on the run.
神乎其技 我没见过人这样厉害
It was an impossible shot. I've never seen anything like it.
你作出的胜利承诺 我没法兑现
You've promised people a victory I can't deliver.
我不是他的对手 毫无胜算
I don't stand a chance against this man.
你不可以这样说
You mustn't talk like that,Vassili.
我们有办法追踪到他的行动
What if I told you we found a way to track his movements?
我们有探子
We've got someone,Vassili.
那探子很接近他
Someone close to him passing us information.
下次你的行动会比他早一步
Next time you will be one step ahead of him.
我保证
I promise.
现在我想请你帮个忙
Now I have a favor to ask.
求我?
From me?
关于丹尼娅的
It's about Tania.
进来
Come in.
他甚至不知道你存在…
He doesn't even know you exist.
但那一刻 你比任何人更接近他
But at that moment,you are closer to him than anyone else on earth.
你通过瞄准器清楚看到他的脸
You see his face through the sight.
看得出他早上有没有剃须…
You see whether he shaved that morning or not.
有没有戴戒指 有没有家室
You can see whether he's married by whether he has a wedding ring on.
你要将狙击的…
It's not like...
不是死物 也不是仅仅一套军服
just firing at a distant shape, not just a uniform.
而是人的脸
It's a man's face.
你会永远记得那些脸
Those faces don't go away.
会在你的脑海里浮现 一张张新的脸孔会不停地更替
They come back and they just-they get replaced by more faces.
丹尼洛夫叫你来说这一番话?
Did Danilov ask you to tell me this?
他喜欢你 想尽力改变你的主意
He likes you very much. I think he'd try anything to change your mind.
他有没有说我为什么想调职?
Did he tell you why I asked for the transfer?
没有
No.
今早总部接到一份名单
This morning,a list arrived at headquarters.
是一批三个星期前…
It was a list of civilians who'd been...
从斯大林格勒押解去德国的平民
rounded up and sent to Germany in a convoy... that left Stalingrad three weeks ago.
我父母当时身在其中
My parents were amongst them.
火车驶了30公里
After 30 kilometers, the German soldiers...
停下来 德军把所有人赶下车
stopped the train and forced everyone out.
在桥中央 德军把大家绑起
In the middle of a bridge, they bound them together,
绑成一对对
two by two.
母与女、夫与妻
Mothers with daughters. Husbands and wives.
德军叫那些人在桥边排队
They... lined them up against the railing,
然后每一对开一枪 以节省子弹
and then they fired a single shot at each pair... to save bullets.
这方法奏效
It worked.
中弹的那个把另一个拖进水里
The bodies of the ones who died dragged the others under the water.
我知道他们死在一起
I know they died together.
他们再也不会分开
They never would have let themselves be separated.
这是科里哥夫的步枪 性能很好
That's Koulikov's rifle. It's a good... rifle.
谢谢
Thank you.
我知道他怎样离开防空洞
I know how he leaves the shelter.
他穿过拖拉机厂
He goes through the tractor factory.
拖拉机厂很大的
The tractor factory is big.
我清楚知道他走的路径
I know exactly where.
他沿着大桶铁格下的沟渠… 一直往前爬
He crawls through a gutter,under a grate where the vats are,
然后从工场走出来
then he goes out from the workshop.
其中有一段路没有掩护
In between the two, there's a place where he's in the open.
那一段路在铁长廊之下
It's under a long,iron foot walk.
1942年11月5日
祝你好运 同志
Good luck,comrade.
我知道他会在哪里等候我
I know exactly where he's waiting for me.
在沟渠上的铁长廊
He'll be on the foot walk over the gutter.
我们从后面袭击他
We'll take him out from behind.
我们沿着喉管 走去工场另一边
We'll get to the other end of the workshop through these pipes.
跟我来！
Follow me.
你从那边去
You go that way. I'll go around this way.
我从这边绕过去 好的
Okay?
糟糕！
Shit!
不要紧
Sergei, you should go back.
你应该回去!  不 我不会有事
一 Go back. 一 No,I'll be all right.
不 回去！
No,you go!
把腿缩进去
Keep your legs in.
来吧
Come on. Come on. Come on.
斯大林同志要你们拼尽全力
Comrade Stalin is asking for one last effort!
祖国的命运危在旦夕
The fate of the motherland is at risk!
你们所珍爱的人也危在旦夕
The fate of all those you love and cherish!
我们今天要为他们奋战
It's for them that we fight today.
听我劝吧 丹尼娅
Listen to me,Tania.
德国向我们发动大举攻击
The Germans are throwing everything at us.
十个士兵中只有一个能活着回来
If they're lucky,one in ten of these soldiers will come back alive.
你受过高等教育 通晓外语
You're highly educated. You know languages.
你截听、解读情报
Every intercept you translate saves hundreds of lives.
能拯救许多同胞 亦能杀敌无数
Every message you decode kills thousands of theirs.
你有责任活下去
You have a duty to survive.
瓦希里擅长开枪 是天生的枪手
Vassili was born to fire a gun. It's what he knows.
你我却另有作用
You and I were born for a different purpose.
瓦希里也会对你说同一番话
If Vassili were here, he would tell you the same thing.
他在哪里?瓦希里在哪里?
Where is he? Where is Vassili?
把头伏下 告诉我枪手在哪里
Keep your head down.Tell me where he is.
躲在管内 丹妮娅 不要出来 把头缩起
Stay into that pipe,Tania. Stay in. Stay in! Get your head in!
慢慢来 不要开枪
Slow down. Don't shoot.
他在那里
He's over there.
见到你前面的柱子吗?
Do you see the pillar in front of you?
我要你到柱子的后面去
I need you to move round behind it.
去吧
Go.
我要你找一大块玻璃
Tania,I need you to find a large piece of glass.
一块玻璃?
Piece of glass.
我后面工厂的左边…
Do you see the kiln...
有座窖 看得见吗?
behind me to the left of the factory?
看不看得见?我听不到
Yes? I can't hear you.
看见 看见
一 Yes. 一 Yes.
看见两扇百叶窗吗?
Do you see... the two louvers?
看见 看不看得见…
一 Yes. 一 Do you see the one...
破了百叶板的那一扇?  看见
with a broken slat? Yes.
我要你这么做
This is what I want you to do.
准备好了吗?  准备好了
一 Are you ready? 一 Yes.
三…二…
Three... two... one...
你好 沙夏
Hello,Sacha.
他真的去那地方了
He was right where you said he'd be.
差不多说中
Nearly there.
他很聪明
He's very clever.
跟我说说他
Tell me about him.
为何不是爸爸而是爷爷教他开枪
Why was it his grandfather taught him how to shoot and not his father?
他爸爸死了 妈妈也死了
His father's dead. His mother too.
他有没有提起爸爸?
Does he talk about his father?
不提 他不认识爸爸
No. He didn't know him.
他有上过学吗?
Did he go to school?
他懂得写字 回很多信
He knows how to write. He answers lots of letters.
女孩的信?
Hmm. Is it girls who write to him?
人人都写信给他
Everyone writes to him.
他在家乡有没有喜欢的女孩?
Is there a girl he loves in his village?
不是在家乡 在这里
Not in his village,here.
那女孩喜欢他吗?
Does she love him?
喜欢 因为他英俊
Yes,because he's handsome.
因为他勇敢 那女孩很漂亮
Because he's brave and she's very beautiful.
我跟她很熟 她是我邻居
I know her well. She's from my neighbour hood.
她上过大学
She went to the university.
他们郎才女貌 将来会结婚
They're handsome together.Later,the two of them will get married.
起码我是这么想的
At least,I think so.
而你呢?沙夏…
And you,Sacha,
你为什么帮德国人?
why are you helping the Germans?
因为德国人比较强 会打胜仗
Because they're stronger. Because they're going to win the war.
也因为你爱吃朱古力
And because you like chocolate,huh?
这些人知道自己活不久
All these people here know they're gonna die.
晚上能够活着回来…
So each night when they make it back,
算是赚了一天
It's a bonus.
对不起
Excuse me.
于是 每一杯茶…
So,every cup of tea,
每一根香烟…
every cigarette...
都成了小小的庆祝
becomes a little celebration.
因为这可能是我们的最后一晚
Because for a lot of us, it maybe our last night.
你在这儿要接受这事实
It's just something you have to accept here.
人难免一死
Everyone has their time.
在森林里 狼只活三年
In the forest, the wolf lives for three years,
驴则活九年
the donkey for nine.
抱歉！这必定是乌拉尔的俗语
So,that's一 that's got to be a proverb from the Urals.
我认为没有道理
It makes no sense to me whatsoever.
驴活得长 因为它有用处
The donkey lives longer because he's more useful.
这绝对有道理
Makes absolute sense.
森林里哪里有驴?
There aren't any donkeys in the forest.
你虚构出来的
You made it up.
那么…我是头驴吗?
So... I'm a donkey?
你和丹尼洛夫这种人得活下来
People like you and Danilov... have to survive this.
你们读过书 受过教育
People who have read books, had an education.
战后重建 需要你们
We'll need you when the war is over.
假如你能活下来呢?
And if you survive?
“无用”的瓦希里会做什么?
What will the useless Vassili Zaitsev do then?
我想在工厂干活
I wanna work in a factory.
爷爷带我进过工厂一次
My granddad took me to a factory once.
高处的铁走廊上… 站着一个人
There was this man there, high up on a-on a foot walk.
他与众不同 不穿蓝工作服
He wasn't wearing blue like the others.
他手下的工人…
The people he was supervising
都不明白自己做什么 不过…
didn't really understand what they were doing. But for him,
他高高在上 就那么简单 一切了如指掌
for him up there, it was simple; it was clear.
我希望自己有朝一日…
And I thought,"One day,
能成为那个人
I could be that man."
拥有不能实现的梦想 真难过
Sad to have a dream you know won't happen.
为什么不可能实现?
Why shouldn't it?
你会长命百岁
You'll outlive us all. Hmm.
你会成为森林里最老的驴
You'll be the oldest donkey in the forest.
德军离伏尔加河有150米
"150 meters stand between the Germans and the Volga.
这举世瞩目的150米…
"Today the whole world is watching these 150meters.
使斯大林格勒成为…
They are what makes Stalingrad..."
战争的…
the capitol...
首都
of the war.
你的朋友丹尼娅…
Your friend,Tania...
你有没有见过她?
have you see her?
她跟狙击队的人在一起
She stays over there now, with the snipers.
告诉少校所有狙击手会进攻工厂
Tell the major we're sending in all of our sharpshooters... to support the attack on the factory.
瓦希里也会参与
Tell him Vassili will be there.
我要跟你谈谈 好
一 I need to talk to you. 一 Sure.
丹尼洛夫   嗯
一 Danilov. 一 Hmm?
别再写我了
You have to stop writing about me.
我根本不是他对手
I'm not gonna get him because I'm not good enough.
他迟早会找到我 会杀掉我
Sooner or later,he's gonna find me, he's gonna kill me.
我警告过你 不准说丧气话
I've warned you before not to talk like this.
今次不同
This time it's different.
你把我吹嘘得
You've built me up...
也过于伟大了
and up into someone I'm not.
我受不了这份量 我想作战
I can't carry that weight anymore. I wanna fight.
像普通士兵那样作战
I want to fight just as a regular soldier.
我明白
I understand.
但你不是普通士兵 你很出色
The thing is,you're not a regular soldier. You're extraordinary soldier.
那只是你编造出来
No,I'm what you've made me.
仅此而已
Nothing more.
为什么现在说这番话?
Why are you telling me this now?
发生了什么事?
Hmm? What's happened?
有什么改变了?
What's changed?
你有没有替我劝劝丹尼娅?
Did you speak to Tania for me?
有   那么..
一 Yes. 一 Well...
她肯回心转意吗?
will she reconsider?
不知道
I don't know.
为了安全 她应该回心转意
She should. She'll be much safer. She should,you know that.
是的
Yeah.
她调职比你容易
It'll be easier to get her reassigned.
德军准备再进攻市中心
The Germans are preparing another offensive in the city center.
我们很需要利用你去激励军心
The propaganda battle is crucial for morale. We need you more than ever.
沙夏！
Sacha. Hold on. Sacha!
把你的消息告诉他
Tell him what you know,Sacha.
沙夏 你好
Hello,Sacha.
少校的军靴沾了尘
There was dust on the major's boots.
少校以为沙夏投靠了敌方
Sacha has the major convinced he's gone over to the other side.
不用我说 你也知他要冒多大险
I don't need to tell you the risk she's taking.
尘是黄色的
The dust was yellow.
全市只有化工厂后面的…
There's only one place where there's dust like that-
小径旁有一大堆黄尘
in the back of the chemical factory, a big heap on the tracks.
干得好
Well done.
沙夏
Sacha...
到外面等我
wait for me outside then.
丹尼洛夫 嗯
一 Danilov, 一 Hmm?
你无权利用他
you had no right to use him.
我没有利用他
No,no,I didn't use him.
他是自愿的
Vassili, he did it of his own accord.
你知道原因吗?
You know why?
因为他信任你
Because he believes in you!
明早我们就会收复化工厂
Tomorrow morning,we're going to take back the chemical factory.
沙夏通知了少校你会去
Sacha's informed the major you'll be there,
你知道应该在哪里埋伏他
so now you know where you have to wait for him.
在突击途中
In the middle of an assault.
我奉命行事 建议你也一样
I'm following orders.I suggest you do the same.
我知道要冒险
Now,I'm aware of the risks.
你会没事的
You'll be fine.
同志
Comrade.
那边现在是德军 昨天是俄军的
That's the Germans up there. And yesterday was the Russians.
我们快到了
We're not very far now.
沙夏
Sacha...
你在玩很危险的游戏
you're playing a very dangerous game.
我想你打胜仗
I want you to win.
看到吗?沿着河一直走去
See there? Keep going along the river.
那里很安全…暂时
It's safe... for a while.
Aah!
他死了
He's dead.
我们在他尸体上找到的
We found this on his corpse.
你再没必要留下来
Your reason for being here has ceased to exist.
请原谅 将军阁下
Pardon me,Herr General,
但我不相信…
but I do not believe一
明晚有飞机往柏林 你要上机
There is a plane bound for Berlin tomorrow evening. You will be on it.
登机前 你必须交出军牌来
Until then,I must ask you for your dog tags.
万一你死掉 俄军就会趁机大肆宣传
Imagine how Russian propaganda would profit from your death.
你死 就要死得无声无息
If you fall, you will fall unknown.
你曾经差点没命
You've already had a near miss.
另外 请收下这十字勋章
Also please take this War Merit Cross.
是追颁给第116步兵师一名上尉
It was awarded posthumously... to a lieutenant of the 116th Infantry Division...
开战不久 他在这里为国捐躯
who fell here during the first days of the battle.
他是我的儿子
He was my son.
码头一失守 万事俱休！
If the landing is captured, everything's lost!
过来！
Come here.
我警告过你 你玩得太多花样！
What did I tell you? You've been playing your fiddle too much!
假如证实他归西 我们就会完蛋
If it's confirmed that he's dead,we're sunk!
你会完蛋！  这不是真的
一 Well,you're sunk. 一 It isn't true.
这是从他们的参谋部截获的
It was intercepted from their staff headquarters.
他们还想怎么样 难道要他们把尸体吊起你才信?
What do they have to do, dangle his body in front of our men?
他们在说谎
They're lying.
好 很好
That's good. Very good.
这样写吧：瓦希里并没有死
Write it,then. "Vassili Zaitsev is not dead.
今早他吃这些早餐
"This is what he had for breakfast this morning.
这是他今早看报的照片
This is a picture of him reading today's newspaper.
随便作吧
" You're the poet".
什么?
What?
不准弃守河畔！
You won't give up the riverbank!
已经死掉一半士兵?我不管！
I don't  care if you're lost half your men!
继续防守 不然就是你自己死掉
Lose the other half, or lose yourself!
他回来没?
Is he back?
就快回来了
He should be back soon.
德军切断路线 所以他才迟了
The German attack cut the lines. That's why he's late.
我们出去一下好吗?
Can we go outside?
我写信向母亲谈起你
I wrote to my mother about you.
她说 战事结束之后
She wanted me to tell you that once this war was over,
无论你有什么需要…
if there's anything you needed anything at all
我们一家都会帮你
our family will be there for you.
你知道我是为你的
You know I'm here for you.
他们说瓦希里已经死了
They're saying Vassili is dead.
瓦希里再也见不到亲人了
Vassili Zaitsev will never see his loved ones again.
投降吧！这是唯一生路！
Surrender! This is your only hope.
你难过?
You're upset.
因为瓦希里死了?
Because Zaitsev is dead?
不用掩饰 不用难为情
You don't have to hide it. There's no shame in it.
你跟他一样是俄罗斯人
You're a Russian like he is.
不要听他们说
Don't listen to them.
这只是宣传
It's just propaganda.
他没有死
He isn't dead.
你知道原因吗?
And do you know why?
因为我还没有杀死他
Because I haven't killed him yet.
告诉你一个秘密吧
I'm going to tell you a little secret.
我只告诉你 因为我信得过你
Only you,because I know I can trust you.
不过 你要发誓保密
But you must swear to me that you won't tell another soul.
愿意发誓吗?
You swear?
我找到一个绝佳地点
I found a terrific spot.
是火车站的出口旁边
It's by the exit from the train station.
我会躲在水塔里面
I'll hide in the water tower.
明天 我在那儿候他
Tomorrow. I'll wait for him there.
他一定会来 你等着瞧吧
You'll see. He'll be there.
他一直都会出现
He always is.
我也要你发誓 从此你留在家里
I also want you to swear that from now on,you'll stay home where you belong.
你肯发誓吗?
Do you swear?
肯吗?
Yes?
好
Good.
瓦希里还活着 不会教我们失望
"We know he's alive. We know he won't fail us.
因为他现就在我们当中
We know because he is a part of us now.
瓦希里打不死
Vassili is eternal."
你去了哪里?
Where have you been?
我们到处找你
We've looked everywhere for you.
你没听到?
Oh,didn't you hear?
我死了
I was dead.
起码崇高的神射手瓦希里…
At least the noble sniper Zaitsev...
已经死去
Vassili was dead.
现实中的
The real one.
我…
Me...
我睡着了…
I was asleep,
错失了机会
and I missed my chance.
瑟缩在一角 躲避一个…
Then,I was curled up in a corner,hiding...
想置我于死地的人
from a man who wants to kill me.
我会向赫鲁晓夫报告
I'll talk to Kruschev.
他会把你调回原本的部队
He'll send you back to your old division.
丹尼娅呢?
一 Where's Tania?
她在防空洞
一 She's at the shelter.
我到过防空洞
I've been to the shelter.
我对她说你没死
I told her you weren't dead.
少校是这样说
The major said so.
他说其他德军在骗人
He said the other Germans were lying.
他说你会在车站等他
He told me you were waiting for him at the station.
瓦希里…
Vassili.
我的小沙夏…不出我所料
My little Sacha. I knew it.
瓦希里 丹尼娅
一 Vassili. 一 Tania.
我早知你没有死
I knew you weren't dead.
你怎知道?
How?
因为我们才刚遇上
Because we only just met.
我长大之后首次祈祷
I prayed for the first time since I was a little girl.
我一睁开眼睛…
When I opened my eyes,
沙夏就站在我面前 报告好消息
Sacha was standing there...waiting to give me the good news.
他比我更爱你呢
I think he loves you even more than I do.
致司令
To the proper military authority,
兹呈报士兵瓦希里…
I'm calling to the commandant's attention the recent changes noticed...
近来作战态度改变了
in the attitude towards fighting of soldier Vassili Zaitsev.
数度试图逃避职责
He has attempted on several occasions to escape his duties,
公开发表悲观言论
voiced doubts on the chances of our victory...
质疑我军胜利的可能
and made defeatist comments in public.
他与纳粹枪手决斗 久未获胜
The inexplicable duration of his duel...
唯一的原因是…
with the Nazi sharpshooter can only be explained by...
他对共产理念缺乏信心
his lack of belief in the communist ideal.
早晨 沙夏
Good morning,Sacha.
他再一次知道我的行踪
Once again,he knew exactly where to find me.
你说奇不奇怪?
Don't you think that's strange?
我的行踪 只有你知我知
Apart from me,only you knew.
我不怪你
I don't hold it against you, Sacha.
你很勇敢
You've done a very brave thing.
你爱自己国家，我很敬佩
You've chosen your camp. I respect that.
但那不是我的阵营
But it isn't my camp.
你我都是军人
We're both soldiers,
你我是敌人 我知道你会谅解的
and we're both enemies, so I know you understand.
我生你气 因为你不留在家里
I'm annoyed with you,little Sacha,for not staying home as I made you swear to.
我生你气 因为你逼我做一件事
I'm annoyed with you for obliging me to do what I'm going to have to do.
你连睡梦中也皱眉头
I've never seen anyone frown so much in their sleep.
你看了我多久?
How long have you been watching me?
整晚
All night.
你不断扯鼻鼾
You've been snoring away happily for hours.
我扯鼻鼾?
I don't snore. Do I?
像猪一样
Like a pig.
我大概也有发开口梦吧?
I suppose I talk in my sleep as well.
是的
Yes.
有件事我想告诉你
There's something I should tell you.
我坐火车来这里的时候…
On the train... coming here...
和你在同一个车厢 不可能
we were in the same car. No.
我见到你
I saw you.
你在看书 然后睡着了
You were reading, and you fell asleep.
我不敢看你 你太漂亮了
I didn't dare look at you, you were so beautiful.
很惊人
It was scary.
之后 我不断想起你
Afterwards,I couldn't stop thinking about you.
想起你就笑
It made me smile.
又想到那些可以拥抱你
And then I thought of all the men who would get to hold you...
逗你发笑的人
who'd make you laugh...
他们多幸运
how lucky they were.
现在我居然可以躺在你身边
And now I'm the one lying next to you.
我有没有扯鼻鼾?  像猪一样
一 Was I snoring? 一 Like a pig.
什么事?
What?
我的天！
Oh,my God!
不要出去！
Oh,no.
天啊 丹尼娅 不能去！
一 Oh,my God! 一 Tania,no.
丹尼娅 不能去！放开我！
一 Tania,no! 一 No,get off me!
放开我！  这正是他的诡计！
一 Get off me! Get off me! 一 It's what he wants!
他会杀死你 放手！等我来!
一 No,he'll kill you. He'll kill you! 一 Let me go!
我跟你出去 他也会杀死我  等我来!
一 I'll run after you,and he'll kill me. 一 Let me go!
放开我！  这正是他的目的 我会干掉他的
一 Let me go! 一 This is what he wants! I'll get him.
我保证会杀死他
I promise I'll get him.
我保证会拿他的枪给你
I'll get his rifle for you. I promise,Tania.
我需要你帮忙
I need you.
费太太 你必须走 斯大林格勒可能沦陷
You have to leave now,Mrs.Filipov. Stalingrad may fall.
最后的船快开了 德军随时攻到
The last of the boats are leaving. The Germans will be here any moment.
我们替你弄到通行证
He's brought you a pass.
你在对岸会很安全
You'll be safe on the other side.
收拾行李 我们送你去码头
Gather your things,and we'll help you carry them to the landing stage.
我不走 这是我的家
I'm not leaving. This is my home.
这是沙夏的家 不可以走
This is my Sacha's home. I can't leave.
费太太 我有件事要告诉你
I have to tell you something, Mrs.Filipov.
这件事难以明白
Something very difficult to understand.
关于沙夏的
It's about Sacha.
沙夏投靠了德军
He's gone over to the Germans.
出卖了国家 他现在跟德军一起
He's betrayed his country.He's with the enemy now.
不会回来了
He won't be coming back.
我的天！
Oh,my God.
他做了叛徒
He's become a traitor.
可怜的小鬼头 他做了什么?
The poor little thing. What has he done?
那么 他会留在那边?
So,he's going to stay over there?
是的
Yes...
他会留在那边
he's going to stay over there.
政委同志 我不应该这样说
I shouldn't be saying this,comrade Commissar,
不过 这样或者更好
but maybe it's for the best.
假如德军打胜 他会安全
If the Germans have won, he'll be safe.
或者对他来说 这是正确选择
I know it's wrong,but perhaps he has made the right choice.
丹尼娅！  丹尼娅！
一  Oh! Oh,Tania! 一  Tania?
一 Oh,Tania! 一 Tania!
天啊
Oh,my God! Oh!
有没有医生?
I need a doctor!
医生！
A doctor!
我有通行证
I have a pass. I have a pass!
你一定要让她上船！
You must let her cross.
求求你
Please!
没用的 她不会活得成
It's useless. She'll never make it.
她会！
No! No,she will!
她是我女儿
She's my daughter! She's my daughter!
求求你！  好吧
一 I beg of you! 一 All right.
你们两个 抬她上船
一 Oh,thank you! 一 Put this one on the boat.
我身体很好 会撤退到对岸
沙夏 保重
他在哪里?
Where is he?
少校在哪里?
Where's the major?
咫尺之间
A few inches from your face.
我一直都很愚昧 瓦希里
I've been such a fool, Vassili.
人性改不了
Man will always be man.
没什么特殊的
There is no new man.
我们努力去创造平等社会
We tried so hard to create a society that was equal,
希望大家不用妒忌别人
where there'd be nothing to envy your neighbor.
可是 人总有令别人妒忌的东西
But there's always something to envy.
一个微笑
A smile...
一份友谊
a friendship.
求之而不可得的东西
Something you don't have and want to appropriate.
在这世上 即使是苏联的世界…
In this world even a Soviet one
总是有贫富差别
there will always be rich and poor.
富于天赋
Rich in gifts...
贫于天赋
poor in gifts.
富于爱情
Rich in love...
贫于爱情
poor in love.
丹尼娅不会回来了
Tania isn't coming back.
她死了 瓦希里
She's dead,Vassili.
给炮弹碎片击中
She was cut down by shrapnel.
事出突然 她该没看到碎片飞来
It was quick.I don't think she even saw it coming.
她本来回来找你
She was on her way back to you.
把费太太送上船之后
As soon as she had seen Mrs.Filipov to the boats,
马上回来找你
she was coming back for you.
她是对的 瓦希里 你是个好人
She was right. You're a good man,Vassili.
我想帮你一个忙
I want to help you, Vassili.
我想做最后一件事
Let me do one last thing.
做一件善事 补偿一下
Something useful for a change.
我帮你把少校引出来
Let me show you where the major is.
不要这样做
Don't do that.
千万不要！
Don't do that!
两个月后
1943年2月3日
今天1943年2月3日…
Today,February3,1943, is an ominous day for Hitler...
对希特勒和无数的德国战俘而言是不祥的一天
and the endless columns of hundreds of thousands of German prisoners.
但却是俄罗斯胜利难忘的一天
It is an unforgettable day of hope for our motherland.
经过了斯大林格勒180天
After 180 days of heroic combat...
奋勇的战斗
in the market city of Stalingrad,
以及我军奋不顾身的作战
and as a result of the valor and self-sacrifice of our soldiers,
我们伟大的红军领袖…
the commander of our glorious Red Army...
接受了法西斯侵略者无条件投降
received the unconditional surrender... of the German fascist invaders.
抱歉 没有 小伙子
Sorry. No,young man,
我在册子里找不到那个名字 请再找找
一 I cannot find...a matching name in the book. 一 Could you check again?
这是这医院地址 这是她的名字
一 This is the address and her name. 一 She is not here.
地址没错 但她不在这里
Yes,this is our address, but we don't have her anymore.
这是你们的地址 很对不起
一 This is the address. She's been here. 一 I'm so sorry.
她写过信给我
She wrote to me.
我查过三次了 她不在这里
I looked three times. She's not here.
我们的确没有丹尼娅这个人 我们爱莫能助
Believe me,there is no Tania Chernova. I can't help you.
对不起
I'm so sorry.
瓦希里数度获颁列宁勋章
更被列入苏联英雄的行列
他所用的步枪…
连同其他战胜纳粹党的标志
至今仍然陈列在…
斯大林格勒历史博物馆里